people love to argue and fight about
almost
everything regarding nutrition but one
thing that seems to be agreed upon
across almost everyone is that you want
to maximize
nutrient intake right you've heard these
things eat nutrient dense or
nutrient-rich foods
and you've heard micronutrients and
macronutrients
help think of the word itself nutrition
or nutritious
it all seems to be centered around this
one concept
nutrients but have you ever stopped to
ask yourself
what the hell does that actually even
mean well like i think my nutrients
means like a lot of vitamins and
minerals
but if we're all going to believe that
this is probably one of the few central
defining core principles of a high
quality diet
we might want to know what nutrients
means
more than just like maybe some vitamins
or minerals i think or something
we can do better than that so in this
episode of 25 minute fizz that's exactly
what i'm going to do
explain to you what are these nutrients
what that means
and we'll cover all of them right so how
do your vitamins and minerals and macros
and all of that
play a role in explaining and
understanding what nutrients are so i'll
take a piece of food and i'll walk you
through exactly what is in
all that food you consume so you can
understand exactly what it means to have
a nutrient
dense diet or nutrient-rich diet
now for those of you that are new to the
crew my name is andy galpin
i'm a full professor and scientist in
the center for sport performance at cal
state fullerton
i've got a phd in human bioenergetics a
master's in human movement sciences
and i've been working with elite
athletes and conducting research on all
things human performance
for almost 20 years now so trust me when
i say this friends
you're now rocking with the best now in
case you haven't heard yet my jam is to
educate
inspire and entertain all of you by
presenting to you the science of
strength conditioning
nutrition and basically everything human
physiology
and i do that by giving away all of my
knowledge for free
in these 5 25 and 55 minute physiology
videos
because i believe so much that this
knowledge
should be free and accessible to anyone
in the world
with a basic internet connection and not
stuck behind the paywall of some
university
or journal now i've been doing this for
a couple of years now and i have to stop
quickly and thank all of you who have
supported me thus far there's no way i
could have done this without all of you
so for those of you friends who've
provided support over the last couple of
years
i can't thank you enough and i promise
if you all keep chipping in
i'mma keep chopping it up and giving you
everything i got
to help you along your way that being
said
let's talk some science oh and before we
get started a fair warning
if any of you have ever been in my class
or worked with me as an athlete you know
i'm not the best with county numbers
so when i say 25 minutes maybe 12 maybe
i don't know close enough all right so
let's start with a piece of food it
doesn't matter what it is but let's
assume it's a giant piece of pizza
fantastic
basically everything inside of it can be
broken down into two major categories
non-nutrients or some call these
anti-nutrients so don't worry about that
for now
and nutrients all right so anything you
see following these categories
on the right-hand side or your left-hand
side will be a nutrient and the other
side of course will be technically
considered a non-nutrient
in order for that distinction to take
place mostly scientists will say that it
has to fall into this category
it has to be used by an organism to grow
reproduce
or survive it can be used in two major
functions
inside the cell in the form of
metabolism or excreted by the cell and
uses structure
think fingernails or a shell in the case
of an animal or
anything like that okay so if it doesn't
hit this definition technically it's
considered to be a non-nutrient that
doesn't mean it's not important or
harmful
it just doesn't hit this category so
inside the nutrients we have three main
subcategories macros minerals and
vitamins
right now you'll see this little
carolina blue line that heads down to
the minerals and the vitamins
so what this means is everything below
these categories
we typically tell people to consume them
in a
minimum or higher fashion so in other
words we say
make sure you have this minimal amount
of this
vitamin or don't go lower than this now
that's separate from what you'll see a
little bit later
and that's not the case as you see for
the macros because that's not your fancy
blue line so that's
kind of also showing you how this whole
schematic is going to work
the blue box is what we consider to be
essential now this doesn't mean and it's
not synonymous with important or
necessary
the technical definition here means your
body cannot synthesize it so you
therefore have to consume it in your
diet
so vitamins just categorically are
almost always
considered essential your body doesn't
do them this is different for different
animals right so again i'm mostly
concerned with humans here because
that's what i assume most of you
are a great example here would be
vitamin c so we know that is essential
we have to consume it in our diet but
other animals
don't they can synthesize it themselves
so wouldn't be considered essential for
them while it
is for us this little gold box if you
will signifies
inorganic so everything else on this
list except for one thing that we'll get
to later
is organic meaning it has a meaning it
has a carbon molecule attached to it
the minerals as you see are not that
they're rocks they're made from the
earth
things that are organic means they're
made from another leaving species
unless you consider the earth to be
alive which whatever don't do that to me
it's not right so everything here is
made by another animal with the
exception of minerals that are just
simply
taken from earth they're rocks basically
google periodic table if you want to
learn more about that the little purple
triangle
you're going to see signifies it has an
acute and by acute i mean like
something on the order of hours or days
response
why is this above macros well if you
consume say 600 grams of carbohydrate
or 48 grams of fat or whatever
differing amounts of different macros
will give you an acute
or you know chronic or acute hours to
days feeling
so if you have that 600 grams of
carbohydrate meal 10 or 15 or maybe an
hour or two later you will feel that
it's also something that you probably
need to pay attention to within your
different meals
that's not true for vitamins and
minerals you can't tell
oh my gosh i just had a lot of vitamin a
or my selenium is really high in this
meal
and in fact you don't even need to
probably change it with you know to
balance your selenium
and your sodium potassium intake
throughout the day for the most part
this is something that doesn't change
usually until you get to multiple days
or weeks
another point on that you can see
differences
in by changing your macronutrients
pretty quickly but you don't really see
that so fixing deficiencies or
toxicities and minerals and vitamins
probably takes you weeks
if not months or you if you are
deficient in carbohydrate right now one
meal can almost
you know can have resounding effects on
that so that's my distinction between
kind of acute
or not coming into our non-nutrients i
break it into three categories
other just because that's an unending
list of things
but the two controversial ones are fiber
and phytochemicals
now you'll see the purple triangle above
fiber because again
if you had like take 50 grams of sodium
root
you will feel what fiber does very
acutely not the same thing for
micronutrients so if you've got extra
polyphenols
in a some blueberries you're not going
to feel that
until you know days or weeks later
you've got the blue
carolina blue lines here because again
like your minerals and vitamins we
typically say hey
don't consume less than this amount of
fiber all right don't consume less than
these amount of
phytochemicals now the phytochemicals
will talk a little bit later and a lot
more in separate videos
we don't have good numbers on those
because we're only just learning about
them
in general we know a lot more about
fiber in fact we can even split that up
like i've done
in the yu fart series of videos into
soluble fiber and insoluble fiber and we
can distinguish things
there but for now i'm just kind of
calling it all globally fiber
so the little colored background i guess
you'll call that like a greenish
blueish weirdest thing for fiber
signifies that
a lot of people consider it to be a
non-nutrient now
i should have said this at the very
beginning but there's not
perfect agreement among nutritional
scientists
what falls into all these categories so
some folks say that fiber is a nutrient
some
don't same with vital chemicals so
there's not perfect distinction here
with fiber it's technically and
generally considered to be a
non-nutrient because it's not used
in growth it's not used in survival
though you could question that a little
bit
and it's not used in reproduction you
can't use it for
metabolism but of course as we just
talked about some forms of fiber you can
partially digest
and you can make an argument well the
bacteria in my gut digests them and then
i get those byproducts in terms of
ketones and short chain fatty acids
okay so again there's an argument that
can be made here
and certainly it's not excreted for
structures so your hair and nails and
stuff are not made of fiber
so to me i give it its own separate
distinction i call it technically not a
nutrient but it's obviously very
important
you would not want to go a day or you
know many hours but really even more
than a couple of days without or very
low fiber
you could seriously have major health
problems now it's basically impossible
to do that
unless you have some very restrictive or
very weird diets
so for the most part it's not something
you have to worry about getting a
minimum of
or getting a maximum phytochemicals are
also a little bit different okay
so they are technically non-nutrients
though as i've said
and this is the last time it will this
is changing rapidly we've just started
to
learn about phytochemicals really in the
last 10 years and so some of them
are now being considered to be nutrients
others are not they're not used in
growth reproduction for metabolism or
excreted however you can make a strong
case vital chemicals are absolutely
necessary for survival especially
mid to late stages of life doesn't seem
like you absolutely have to have them
for
pre-puberty although my guess is we will
learn that that is the case eventually
but we just don't have the science so
don't think of this as they've been
proven to not be important think of this
as we just
don't know yet so technically we can't
scientifically say
yes with the exception of
more and more data coming out on the
survival aspect of
phytochemicals and phytonutrients so
that's why it gets its own
green text in black's box and saying
it's not technically a nutrient
according
to many but it's important and basically
nutrient in fact
i would imagine if i redo this video in
some amount of short years
i will slide that over into the nutrient
category
now as i mentioned i will cover the
phytochemicals a lot in separate videos
because there's over 25 000 of them and
that list is growing you can basically
split them into two major categories
carotenoids and polyphenols
and those are sub then subdivided into
dozens of countless other
subcategories so i'll leave
phytochemicals and
in fact some people call them
phytonutrients for that same argument
but photochemicals is the better term
let's move on and then talk about your
macros you're more familiar with these
and the major distinction between a
macro is two things here
number one you see that they now have a
pinkish line and that's because we tend
to give people recommendations in terms
of don't exceed this amount
so you'll notice with fiber
phytochemicals minerals and vitamins we
say don't have less than this but with
macros we tend to tell people
don't have more than this now of course
there are minimum requirements for these
macros again
they're they're needed right you would
survive
or starve i mean without them but that's
i'm talking about the general guidelines
right so don't have more than this
amount this amount this amount
etc the orange box surrounding them
signifies that these are converted into
smaller molecules
in the process of releasing energy so we
can make what's called atp
and the final product is co2 and h2o
now this is again different because you
cannot use minerals or vitamins or most
of fiber and no phytochemicals
for energy so this is it when we say
macronutrients
these are the three we're generally
talking about and of course the fourth
one being water
now water is special because it is the
inverse we typically say
don't consume less than x amount and see
any of my videos on
optimizing hydration for those numbers
water is also special because it is the
one macronutrient that is not caloric
it's not used for energy production in
any way
and technically it should have like a a
gold box because it of course is
inorganic
all right it's the only other one i was
loading to earlier that's on this list
that
doesn't have a carbon molecule attached
to it
the other fun distinction about water is
it is the only thing on this
list that is absolutely essential and
required for all living
beings right so as i said earlier
some animals and organisms they may or
may not need
protein or carbs or other things but
water is
essentially and required for everything
that is alive which makes it very unique
and special and why we always tell you
make sure you're super hydrated
let's start with the first macronutrient
that is protein and you can generally
split this into
three major categories the first one
being the black box and these are what
are considered to be non-essential
nutrients again does not
amino acids rather does not mean they
are unimportant simply means you do not
have to consume them in your diet
because your body can produce
enough of them on its own or
endogenously that's what that means
the other category or the essential ones
which the exact opposite you have so you
have to consume these in your diet
and again we have the blue line there so
we tend to say here's the minimum amount
of valene or tryptophan etc
to consume it's also blue because they
are
essential the i'm not going to go
through all nine of the essential ones
in this video that again will be in
separate ones but the one thing i do
want to draw your attention to is
leucine because we know that has a
particularly
important role with things like muscle
growth with exercise and since i'm an
exercise scientist
that's the thing i care most about all
right i don't really care about
other stuff obviously the only thing in
this world i'm consumed about is
maximizing muscle
i mean i know i didn't need to say that
because look at me but
you get the third category here
under protein is what are things that
are called
conditionally essential so
your body can produce these on their own
but in some special circumstances it
can't produce
enough this is classic in common with
things like
fetal development or maybe even
prepubescent or even as adults things
like if you're trying to maximize
hypertrophy you might be able to create
some arginine or glycine but you maybe
don't produce
enough to maximize muscle growth so
that's what it means to be condition
essential
and that's why those boxes are outlined
in blue
moving over to fat you've got wait a
minute
why do i skip carbs oh that's right
folks
they're not essential
don't shoot me it doesn't mean they're
not needed
or important or you can perform
optimally without them i didn't say
any of those things you're liars
i didn't say that i just mean
technically they're not essential
because your body can produce a ton of
them
okay i can't wait to see people misuse
what i just said there
anyways on to fat three magic categories
here
the first one is what i call the rest
and that's because there are a
ton of fatty acids and i did not want to
take the time or honestly the space
to list them all here so you can look
all those things up and those are
clearly in black so they're
non-essential doesn't mean they're not
important
you get it the other two categories
conditionally essential dhea
which is an omega-3s why that three is
there and alpha
gamma linoleic acid and omega six so
these are very common for example you
need these to consume these when you're
developing as a young child because dha
in this example is so important for
brain development
but by the time you could become an
adult again it moves into non-essential
doesn't mean you don't want to consume
it
or that you wouldn't benefit from
consuming more but they're technically
non-essential the two essential
amino acids are here and often difficult
to pronounce so
we'll go slow the first one is alpha
alpha alpha linolenic acid
and that's an omega-3 fatty acid the
second one is simply linoleic acid so
notice the difference of the n there
functionally what that means is you have
to consume enough of them and again
we've got a blue line there because we
say make sure you get at least this
minimal amount and so a lot of folks
don't realize that
these two fatty acids are actually
essential
moving on then to your minerals
when we typically say macro we almost
always assume you're talking about
protein carbs of fat but a common
distinction here are your macro minerals
and they're called that because as you
can see in blue they are essential
but two because they're consumed in
really high quantities
i think of things like calcium
you're probably getting prescribed grams
per day
the rest of the things on this list
you'll see are almost always
milligrams per day or micrograms per day
so we call these your macrominerals
now you'll also notice that there's a
little bit of distinction here there's a
red line outlining the minerals and
that's because there are what i call to
be toxicity limits there are known and
somewhat realistic
toxicities associated with these now as
i've said a thousand times
everything has a hormetic curve
everything has a toxicity dose
right you can eat too many carbs and die
you could eat too much fiber or water
and drown
etc so everything has a deficiency and a
toxicity limit
but we make special distinction here
because like this is what i call them
they're somewhat realistic
it is very difficult to be to reach
toxic levels
of any of the things in this list which
is normal food consumption
most of the problems we see here are
from supplementation now that's not
always the case and i'll delineate that
out in many separate videos
but that's generally the rule so that's
again why i call it known
and somewhat realistic if we go back to
example of
fiber one of the other reasons people
don't technically call it
a nutrient is because it does not have a
known deficiency or toxicity limit
the minerals we do so we have a pretty
good idea of what happens when you have
this below this minimal threshold of
chloride or this minimal threshold of
calcium or whatnot
and by the same token what the opposite
or upper limit is what they'll call
these things
uh nutrition think of sodium right
that's the easiest example
very commonly way too much sodium is
consumed in people who don't exercise
and consume way too much overly
processed or over salted
foods athletes folks that eat mostly
natural
or whole real foods don't have that
issue so they can have much higher
sodium concentrations
and not worry about okay you can see the
hydration videos and some other videos
i'll do on electrolytes and
salt in general our next category though
of minerals
is what we call trace or ultra trace and
that's generally because in the pink box
you consume
less than 100 milligrams per day again
that's sometimes like
a tenth or a 50th of the amount of say
sodium
or chloride you can consume in a day so
it's very small amount so
they are clearly very important they
have known toxicity limits so they're
still under the umbrella of the red
or the mirror and you can see the whole
list of them there iron zinc copper
iodine
etc also still essential you'll notice
everything
so far on the category mineral is
considered essential
and then there is the rest right so
there's all kinds and again an
unending list of these things just to
look at your periodic table right
fluoride and bromide and arsenic and
aluminum and all these things
we don't know that you need to have any
of these really in your body and some of
them are actually very toxic very
quickly
and they're very they're generally con
even though there's things like arsenic
and peaches and stuff like that it's
such an incredibly small amount that
it doesn't have any functional role
moving on into our last category of
vitamins we break these up into two
separate
types of vitamins fat soluble and
water-soluble so the fat soluble ones i
can split up and give three major
distinctions so we're talking about
vitamins a e
k and d now d is separated and you can
see it's actually conditional
because as we know we can get vitamin d
from the sun so
it is essential we have to have a
certain amount of it but we don't
necessarily have to have it from our
diet we can get it from the sun so it's
a little bit
separated over there now technically
all of your vitamins have known and
somewhat realistic toxicity levels
but i frankly don't agree with most of
them a is fairly common especially with
supplementation there are very known
very quick and very realistic problems
with overconsumption of vitamin a
vitamin e and k technically have limits
but
i i don't really see it in the data i
haven't seen that many examples of
people having huge problems with enk
even with supplementation and vitamin d
especially
a typical dose of vitamin d is like 5
000 ius per day
there are many reports of people taking
10 12 15 times that
for months on end and not really having
any problems
and so i don't really if you look at the
textbooks you're going to see
vitamin d is a toxicity but i honestly
don't really consider it to be that big
a deal
also because the fix is so easy if you
just reduce the vitamin d
intake or just take it way down then it
goes back to normal pretty quickly so
it's not really one that i consider to
be you know a big concern for toxicity
in terms of your water soluble ones now
the major distinction here between fat
soluble and water-soluble is
technically what they dissolve in but
for your body
it means this the fat soluble ones you
store so this is one of the reasons why
vitamin a
which is i'm pretty sure primarily
stored in a liver
has a toxicity problem because if you do
over consume it it will be stored and
that
increase in stored abundance is where
the problems start the fat soluble ones
if you don't
eat or don't if you over consume them
they generally just going to get
excreted in urine
so they have a much lower chance of
causing toxicity so you don't even see
any of those on the board here
again i know you can technically get
vitamin c toxic but
you're going to pee most of it out and
it's not going to have any problems it
doesn't mean you want to just over
consume any of the water-soluble ones
prophylactically
in fact we have seen cases of excess
vitamin c and vitamin e consumption
blocking things like exercise adaptation
so reducing hypertrophy
and stuff like that so i will talk in
separate videos about how you optimize
these levels and
so there's no just like free passes you
can't just consume vitamins
and nauseam but we don't have a super
huge issue with if you take double or
triple the amount of
rda recommendations of you know thiamine
or something or riboflavin
you're going to be just fine for the
most part all right
so again i'll talk about all those
videos later
so that's it i think we finished in
around 25 minutes or so so hey
if you're new this is pretty good as i
mentioned be on the lookout for all
these other videos i've got coming on
the realms particularly of the nutrients
so i've done a lot on the macros you can
check
all those out i'd recommend starting
with the
you know clearing clearly clarifying the
confusion videos with the macro with the
protein carbs and fat type of stuff
um see the fart videos for anything you
want to know about fiber see the
hydration videos for anything you want
to know about water
and in the next well basically the rest
of this year i'm gonna be dropping a ton
on the other stuff phytochemicals
minerals and vitamins
that's all coming down the pipe so again
i appreciate all your support
hope you enjoyed this if you want to
support what i'm doing you know what to
do subscribe like all that stuff share
it around
that's honestly the best way so thank
you for your attention
i hope you enjoyed and we will see you
later for a
fantastic discussion of some really
small nutrients
they're going to make your life a little
bit better and probably perform better
[Music]
peace